OK.
Let's get started.
So welcome back, everyone.
So today we're going to
talk about parallelism.
And remember in
the last week, we
introduced how to make a single
GPU go fast by writing kernels.
And we really looked
inside this GPU.
And this week,
we're going to talk
about how to leverage
multiple GPUs to make
your code go even faster.
So the picture you
should have in your head
is something like this.
So for the last week, we
focused on one of these boxes,
where you have your GPU.
Remember, you have your High
Bandwidth Memory, HBM, L2 cache,
L1 cache, registers, and a bunch
of streaming multiprocessors.
So now the picture
gets extended,
because instead of having
one GPU, you might have four,
you might have 1,000 GPUs.
And those are going
to be connected.
And I'll talk later
about how those GPUs are
going to get connected.
And then you're going
to have to figure out
how to leverage all of this
compute to train models.
So in both cases, meaning
both in the single GPU case
and in the multi-GPU case,
as we'll talk about today,
the situation is kind of
similar if you zoom out,
which is that the compute,
the arithmetic logic units,
the tensor core, and so on,
is far away from your data.
And far away for a single
GPU means all the way
over here in HBM.
And now if you have multi GPUs,
the thing that you need here
might be all the way
on a different GPU,
and you're going to have to
shuffle that over somehow.
But the same
principles are going
to be the same,
because the game is
to orchestrate the computation
to try to avoid data transfer
bottlenecks.
It's very easy to
use a ton of GPUs,
but it's hard to use
them effectively.
So taking a little
bit of liberty,
we can think about the
generalized hierarchy
where at the local
level next to the SMs
a single node single GPU
where you have an L1 cache
shared memory.
This was the fastest.
And then you had HBM, which
we lamented was so slow.
But in this lecture, HBM is
going to be considered fast.
Now we're going to think about
the single node multi-GPU
setting where the GPUs
are going to be connected
via NVLink and NVSwitch.
And then finally, the
multi-node and multi-GPU,
where we have to
resort to InfiniBand
and ethernet depending
on what network you have.
So last week, we talked
about various tricks
for in reducing memory
accesses, fusion and tiling.
Read into shared memory,
do as much as you can,
and then write it back out.
And this week,
we're going to talk
about how you can reduce
the amount of communication
across GPUs by replicating
and sharding appropriately.
So why do you do multi-GPUs?
The obvious answer is,
well, you want to scale.
But to put a finer point on
it, there's really two reasons.
One is that your parameters
or activations or gradients
and optimizer state don't fit on
the HBM memory of a single GPU.
So B21 has 192 gigabytes.
If you're training a 1
trillion parameter model,
that's not going to
fit on a single GPU.
And the other reason is that
even if your model could
fit on a single
GPU, you might want
to leverage more GPUs by
splitting everything up
to train faster.
So sometimes there
will be some decisions
to be made because you could
fit everything on GPUs,
but you have fewer cores.
But if you spread
it out, then you're
going to have to pay the
communication bandwidth.
So that's some
calculation you're
going to have to do to figure
out how to parallelize.
So just one note here is that
so far this lecture is Python.
You execute it and you
can just show everything.
Now, in this lecture, if
you run this directly,
it uses multiprocessing.
But when I trace through
it, I'm putting in some
of special single process mode.
So if you want to
see the standard out
for this lecture run in
the multiprocessing setup,
you can click here.
And I'll show this as we
go through the lecture.
But just remember as we
step through this lecture,
we're not actually
doing multiprocessing,
because we're just stepping
through single lines of code.
So this lecture is going
to include two parts.
One is we're going to
learn about the building
blocks of distributed
communication and computation,
starting with the
programming model.
Talk a little bit
about the hardware.
Start to implement
things in Torch,
which you're going to do
on your assignment two.
And then the second
part is we're going
to look at actual training.
We're going to look at
three types of parallelism.
Data parallelism,
tensor parallelism,
pipeline parallelism.
Each is going to cut up our
model in different ways.
We're going to do this
for MLPs rather than
the full transformer.
But it's really the
core computation
is going to be shown here.
So let's dive in.
So the first thing to
talk about is these things
called collective operations.
So collective operations
are these primitives from
distributed programming
that go back to the '80s.
So the idea of parallel
programming is very old.
It wasn't invented
for LLM training.
And it's still the case
that these primitives
are the ones that we use today.
And here, collective
just means that you're
specifying a general
communication
pattern or a template
across multiple devices,
rather than managing
point to point how
this GPU is going to
communicate with another GPU.
And this is going
to be much easier,
and the system can do a
lot more work for you.
So this is a very tried
and trued interface
for doing parallel programming.
So the general
setup is as follows.
The terminology here
is a little bit--
I find it a little bit
strange, but this is standard
in parallel programming.
The idea is that you
have a bunch of ranks
where rank corresponds to a
particular device, in our case
a GPU.
It could be a TPU.
But the point is that you have,
let's say, four ranks here.
The world size corresponds
to the number of devices,
so the world size here is four.
So there is a few operations
we're going to go through.
Broadcast, scatter,
gather, reduce,
all gather, reduce scatter,
all reduce, and all to all.
And each of these
operations is going
to specify how this
set of ranks or devices
is going to transfer
some amount of data
slash compute with it to
some other set of devices.
So the first three, broadcast,
scatter, gather, reduce,
are really just warm
ups, I would say.
They allow you to get a sense of
how these collective operations
work, but they're
not really going
to be the ones that are
driving most of training.
All gather, reduce
scatter, and all
reduce are the
ones that are going
to show up again and again for
distributed training of language
models.
And finally, all
to all I'll just
mention here, which
is important for MOEs,
but we're not going to
actually spend too much time
on this this lecture.
OK, so let's dive in with
the simplest operation, which
is broadcast.
So in broadcasting,
you have a rank 0.
It could be any rank, but let's
just say for sake of picking
one, rank 0, has
some tensor 0123.
And it broadcasts
it to all the ranks.
So at the end of this operation,
we have that each of the ranks
has the same tensor on it.
That should be pretty
straightforward.
And this, again,
doesn't really show up
in the core path of training.
Generally, broadcasts are
used for initialization,
where let's say you initialize
a load initial checkpoint
and then you broadcast
it to all the ranks.
So something that's
done like once.
So the second
operation is a scatter.
And a scatter basically says,
I have a tensor at rank 0
who is split up
into the world size.
And I'm going to
basically scatter
my tensor onto the other ranks.
So rank 0 gets 0,
the zeroth component.
Rank 1 gets this, rank 2 gets
this, and rank 3 gets that.
So again, this is
not directly used,
but scatter is an
important stepping stone
to understand reduced scatter.
So, as the name implies,
scatter just takes a big tensor
at one place and spreads it
out onto multiple places.
And you can see how
this might be helpful,
because you want
all the GPUs you're
scattering to do some
local computation
on the different parts.
So the inverse of
scatter is scatter.
So this should be
very predictable.
The input is you have a bunch
of pieces, each of which
reside on a particular rank.
And then when you
do a gather, that's
with respect to a
particular rank, rank 0,
it's going to just concatenate
all the pieces together.
Again, gather isn't
directly used,
but it's going to be a stepping
stone to understand all gather.
So next is reduce.
So those of you who do
functional programming are
probably familiar
with what reduce is.
It's exactly the same.
The idea is that you start
in the same starting point
as a gather.
And where the tensor is split
up across multiple-- well,
you have some piece of data on
each of the different ranks.
And then you're going
to apply your reduction
operation to all of these and
get that in, put that on rank 0.
So in this case, if you
do a reduction with sum,
then you add these
all up, you get six.
So you can think about
gather as a reduction
where the operation is
concatenation, if you will.
And of course, reduce is
important to understanding
all reduce.
So let me pause there.
Those were just the warm
ups. Just in case people
have any questions about what
a collective operation is,
broadcast, scatter,
gather, reduce.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE] NumPy, where is it?
So the question
is, is this related
to broadcasting and NumPy?
I mean, I think it's
conceptually the same idea,
where you have one thing
that goes to many things.
Like in NumPy, if
you have a scalar,
get broadcast to a tensor.
But the instantiation, this is
for collective communication.
So it's a bit different.
So let's move on to
something more interesting.
So all gather is what
you do to-- basically,
you perform gather to all
ranks, not just rank 0.
So remember what gather does.
It basically takes all
the different pieces
and it just puts it
on one rank, rank 0.
And now all gather just does
it for every single rank.
That's what the all is for.
All means do it for all the
output to all the ranks,
and gather is what you're
doing to all the ranks.
So this is going
to come up a bunch.
It's not important that you
understand this statement
precisely, but later we'll
see that each rank holds
part of the parameters.
And then what you
need to do is all
gather the parameters to
get the full parameters
for the full forward pass.
So in general, as
we're doing training,
we're going to see a lot of
this gather to do something
and then scatter and then
gather and scatter again.
So reduce scatter is performing
reduce on each dimension
and then scattering the results.
So let's say you have four
devices and each of them
has some vector.
And so when we did a reduce
before, we just had 0123,
and that got reduced to 6.
But now reduce scatter says
that for each component
of this tensor, I'm
going to do a reduction,
and then I'm going to put
it on a different rank.
So the first dimension, I'm
going to add these up, I get 6.
Now, for the second dimension,
I'm going to add these up.
I get 10.
For third dimension, I'm
going to process these.
For the fourth dimension,
I'm going to process those.
So where this is going to show
up, just to foreshadow things,
after the backward pass, when
you sum what you're going to do
is each GPU will be dealing
with different data.
And what you're doing is you
need to sum all of the gradients
from the different shards.
And then you're going to
redistribute this storage.
And then finally, all reduce.
If you understand all reduce
gather and all gather,
it's basically you do one
and then you do the other.
So what this does is reduce
scatter, the same input as we
had before.
And remember, in
reduce scatter, we
had 6, 10, 14, and 18
sit on different ranks.
And the all gather
part of all reduce just
puts them all on the same--
everything on the same node.
So all reduce is in some sense
the easiest to understand.
You have a bunch of tensors.
You reduce, in this case, some.
And then you replicate
them on all the nodes.
So we're going to see
this one actually first
when we do a data parallel
where we sum the gradients
and then we replicate
the full parameters.
So that's where we're
actually going to start.
So maybe just focus your
attention on all reduce.
Later, we're going to see how
to get to fancier things like 0
or FSDP.
We need to break the all reduce
into reduce scatter and all
gather, because then
you can intervene
and you can manage
things a bit more.
But for the basic version,
all reduce is fine.
Finally, all to all.
This one is, in some
ways, the most general.
You basically specify how each
rank sends a particular message
to another rank.
And so here's a simple
example where you
have the same input as before.
And what this is
saying is that I
want to send 0 to this
element to rank 0,
meaning keep it myself.
I'm going to send
one to rank 1, two
to rank 2, and three to rank 3.
And then if I'm rank 1, I want
to send four to rank 0, five
to rank 1, six to rank
2, and seven to rank 3.
So basically, the
position here is
going to denote
which rank is going
to be the ultimate destination.
And so if you look at
the output, what happens
is that the first rank is
going to receive everyone
who sent everything in column
0, because all these ranks are
sending these things to rank 0.
Similarly, for rank
1, all of the ranks
are sending this column to
rank 1, and so on and so forth.
So this is going to be useful
when for training MOEs.
And the intuition
here is that each rank
has both a split of the data
and also a subset of experts.
And basically, and the
key idea of the MOE
is that it's dynamic routing.
You have to look at
your data to figure out
which experts you need to
route those activations to.
So it ends up being a
all to all communication.
So if everything were balanced,
meaning that every rank sent
the same number of bytes
to every other rank,
then all to all, you
can think about it
as essentially a transpose.
If you think about this as
a matrix, all you're doing
is transposing that matrix.
But in general, all to all
also handles unbalanced splits.
And I'm not showing
this here, but you
can configure it to
send any number of bytes
to any other rank.
But in general,
you want the splits
to be as balanced as possible.
So remember
[INAUDIBLE] MOE lecture
where we had load balancing to
make sure that things were as
balanced as possible.
So morally, the ideal
goal is to have all
to all look kind of like this.
So just to summarize, maybe a
few helpful tips to remember
the terminology, because
I just went through quite
a few different operations.
So reduce is,
well, it's reduced.
It performs on some of
associative commutative
operation.
Could be some, could
be max, could be min.
Scatter is the inverse gather.
Scatter distributes,
gather centralizes.
And all just means that the
destination is all devices.
So that explains all
reduce and all gather.
Let me pause there
to take any questions
about collective communications.
Yeah?
For operations such as gathering
where we basically [INAUDIBLE]
to rank 0, does that
rank 0 [INAUDIBLE]?
Is it a particular GPU every
time or can that rank 0 change?
Yeah.
So the question is when you
do a gather or a reduce,
the target where you write the
output, right now I said rank 0.
You'll see later in
the code, you basically
specify the GPU ID or the
rank and it goes there.
So it doesn't have to be
determined way in advance,
but it has to be
determined basically
when you execute the call.
Cool.
Anything else?
Yeah.
These are just conceptual
building blocks, right?
They're not actually
[INAUDIBLE].
Are these the
actual [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, so the question is, are
these just conceptual building
blocks or are they code?
So I'm showing these right now
as just conceptual building
blocks, but we'll
very quickly see how
these are implemented in code.
So before getting
into the code, I
want to talk a bit
about the hardware,
in particular how
GPUs are connected,
because we already
what's inside a GPU.
So let's talk about
networking in general.
So this is a very
classic picture.
You can tell from this
very old looking image
that this is how computers,
I mean, generally work.
So you have this server and
then you have a bunch of CPUs.
There's a PCIe bus, which you
connect things like your--
or used to connect things
like your mouse and keyboard.
And then you have a bunch
of GPUs sitting off of them
and you have some RAM.
And then this
computer is connected
to ethernet to another computer,
and so on and so forth.
So this is a particular setup.
It's a particular topology.
And GPUs on the same node, you
use PCIe to communicate and GPUs
on different nodes, you have to
go all the way through ethernet.
So this is like if you
bought your gaming GPU
and you had hooked it up with
your friend and was like,
I'm going to train
some big model.
That's what you
would have to do.
But if you're really
serious about training,
then things look more like this.
This is the picture I
showed in the very beginning
where you have the
GPU and there's
something called NVLink and
NVSwitch and InfiniBand.
So the typical setup is this.
And these numbers,
eight is typical,
but this 256 is kind of made up.
So typically, you have
eight GPUs per node.
And these are connected via
NVIDIA's NVLink to a switch.
And just for calibration,
if you use NVLink 5,
then you're getting
1.8 terabytes
per second of total bandwidth.
And remember, HBM for B200
was 8 terabytes per second.
So it's about 4x slower.
So I mean, this is
still pretty fast
if you think about going
between devices, but obviously,
not as fast as high
bandwidth memory,
which is much slower than
shared memory or L1 cache.
So basically, NVLink
connects to the switch,
which means that from a
programming perspective,
you can think about GPUs as
connected to any other GPU.
You go GPU to any other
GPU, and the hardware
takes care of transmitting
that to the switch,
and the switch routes it.
So typically, what you will
also have is that at some point,
you can't have
NVSwitch and NVLink.
Because as your
number of GPUs grows,
then you're going to have to
put these nodes into pods, which
are connected by InfiniBand.
And the way InfiniBand
works is that now there's
a bit more the-- so now the
GPU doesn't connect directly
to another GPU.
It has to go through PCIe
and goes through this kind
of special InfiniBand cable.
And you see that the speeds
are much, much lower.
And then finally, if you
run out of InfiniBand
and you have these
huge pods, then
you need to connect
them via ethernet.
And in ethernet, you
have to go through PCIe
and that actually goes through
the CPU, which as we'll see,
is even slower.
So it's kind of analogous to
the kind of memory situation.
The more nodes you have, then
the slower it's going to be.
You can't have an NVSwitch
handling 100,000 GPUs.
So one note is that I
alluded to this bypassing
the CPU, which is going to be an
important thing from a hardware
perspective.
So if you have traditional
ethernet, what happens
is that the GPU has to talk to
the CPU to get its data copied.
So it basically has to
copy the data to this.
The CPU has a kernel
socket buffer.
Here kernel means
not the GPU kernel,
but the CPU, traditional
notion of a kernel.
And then it has to build
some network packets,
copy to the network interface,
and then ship it over.
So this generally
introduces a lot of latency.
And so there's this technology
called Remote Direct Memory
Access, RDMA, which allows a
GPU to directly write or read
from another GPU's memory
without using the CPU at all.
So obviously, if you're in
NVLink land and NVSwitch land,
then you have RDMA.
InfiniBand also supports RDMA.
So if you're connected
via InfiniBand,
then you can directly have
GPUs connect to each other
without involving the CPU.
But standard ethernet does not.
There's two notable
advancements I will mention.
So NVIDIA has been
really pushing
the limits on what you can do
with larger and larger pods.
So they have four of basically
the B200's and the B300's.
They have something
called NVL72,
which means that they have
these trays of eight GPUs
but have nine of them.
And so basically, at
the end of the day,
you have 72 GPUs that are
all kind of NV switched
into one NVLink domain.
And if you remember, the NV
link speeds are very fast.
So normally, if
you're mortal, you
think, well OK, I
have eight GPUs that
are interlinked really fast.
And then outside of that, then
things get slowed down a lot.
But if you have a
lot of money, you
can buy this really
fancy hardware
and you can get really fast
interconnects up to 72 GPUs.
And the other thing
I'll mention is
that I said standard ethernet
doesn't support RDMA,
but there has been progress
on the ethernet front as well.
So there's something
called RoCE, RDMA
over converged ethernet,
where the ethernet actually
bypasses the CPU.
And this is sort of their
answer to InfiniBand.
So InfiniBand generally
is very expensive,
as is a lot of NVIDIA products.
But you can get pretty
good performance
by using RDMA over
converged ethernet.
And Meta had some paper showing
that they were exploring this.
So [INAUDIBLE] may or
may not have been trained
over converged ethernet.
So that's just a brief overview
of what the hardware looks like.
You have GPUs.
They're connected via NVLink
to NVSwitch over some domain,
maybe 8, maybe 72.
And then it's
InfiniBand from there.
And now let's talk about
how do you program this.
So at the very lowest level,
there's something called
the NVIDIA Collective
Communications Library,
NCCL or "nickel," which
translates the collective
operations, the all
reduce, reduce broadcasts,
into the actual low level
packets that are sent between
GPUs.
So what a NCCL does
is when you use NCCL,
it's basically like saying,
I want to all reduce.
And then NCCL goes
and figures out what
is the topology of the
hardware, figures out
the path between
different GPUs, and then
it actually launches the GPU
kernels to send and receive
data.
Because at the end
of the day, remember,
everything that runs
on a GPU is a kernel.
So there are communication
kernels as well
that actually do
communication with other GPUs.
So we're not going to look
too much more into NCCL,
but just know that it exists.
And then we're going to
actually go to PyTorch.
So maybe before that, any
questions about hardware?
Yeah.
Can you describe--
there's a rack and a tray.
Can I describe physically a rack
and a tray, like what a rack is
and what a tray is?
So for the NV72, so I'm
not a hardware expert,
but a rack, I mean,
is literally, I mean,
you've seen data centers,
literally a rack.
And each tray is
something that has--
so the G stands
for a [? great. ?]
So there's two CPUs.
And each CPU is
connected to four GPUs.
So each tray has
eight GPUs on it.
And they're stacked
and everything
is connected to this NVSwitch.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so the question is,
what is the difference between
[INAUDIBLE].
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So RDMA, you can think about
it as more of a desiderata.
RDMA means that one
GPU can read and write
from another GPU's memory.
And there's multiple
ways to do RDMA.
One is to use
NVLink and NVSwitch
and another way is
to use InfiniBand.
So InfiniBand and
NVSwitch and NVLink
are more the hardware, what
pieces, what cables and switches
are there.
And RDMA is more
operation, what happens
when you're communicating.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
For example, this
[? advancement ?] RDMA
over converged ethernet
is another way to do RDMA.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah?
Is NCCL optimized for
multi-node clusters?
Because obviously, it seems
intuitive [INAUDIBLE].
But for RDMA based processes,
would NCCL be optimal for that?
So the question is,
is NCCL optimized
for multi-node clusters?
So I don't know the details
of how they have or have not
optimized it.
All I can say is that NVIDIA
has been basically optimizing
their entire stack for
inference and training
of these large models, because
their main customers are
the major providers
of language models.
So I would be surprised if they
haven't thought of optimizing
for those type of workloads.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, what
happens if you have nine GPUs?
How do you distribute the
workload across those?
I guess it kind
of depends on how
the nine lands in your setup.
For example, a lot of
times you'll have--
let's say you have
eight GPUs per node.
So then the ninth one would
be on a different node.
And if you don't have
NVLink connecting them,
then that's going to be
really bad, because that's
going to be one node
which is not providing
that much compute and also very
expensive to communicate with.
But if you, let's
say, had everything
were connected by
NVSwitch, then it
would be much more reasonable.
One more question and
I'm going to move on.
So how is this
different from TPUs?
So [INAUDIBLE] described
TPUs a bit more.
So I mean, let's see.
What can I say
quickly about this?
So TPUs are generally
much simpler objects.
I'm not too familiar
with the details of what
each of these components
corresponds to,
but maybe we can talk
about it offline.
So let's actually
get down to some code
to take advantage
of this hardware.
So PyTorch conveniently
has a torch
distributed library
that provides
a clean interface into
these collective operations.
So you don't have to
explicitly think about NCCL.
And in fact, this library also
supports different backends
for different hardware.
So if you are on GPUs, then
you would use the NCCL backend.
And if you were on
CPUs, then there's
something called gloo
which still allows you to--
like I said, parallel
processing has been around
for a long time before GPUs.
And you can do these collect
operations on CPUs as well.
This library also supports
higher level models
and algorithms such
as SFTP, but we're not
going to use those in the course
because we're building things
from scratch.
All right.
So let's walk through
some basic examples
of collective operations.
So there's this
function called spawn,
which takes another
function I'm going to call,
and it says I'm going to run
this replicated four times where
four is the world size.
So let's see what this does.
This is actually a
wrapper I wrote just
to hack around the fact that
I can't do multiprocessing
in this lecture.
So normally what
you would do is you
call Torch's
multiprocessing.spawn
and you call the function.
But I'm going to do this branch
which disables distributed.
So let's just go through that.
So now I'm in this
function that it's
supposed to be running
asynchronously for each process.
So remember, world size
is the number of processes
and the rank is either 0 or 1
or 2 all the way up to world
size minus 1.
And so there are
world size number
of these functions
that are each running
on a process at the same time.
So I'm on rank 0 right now.
So what do I do?
There's a setup.
You basically configure the
master address and port.
Notice that this is not
actually how the GPUs are
going to communicate.
This is more for general
metadata and coordination.
The actual data
goes through NCCL.
Otherwise, it would
be very, very slow.
And if you have Cuda
available, then you
can use the NCCL backend.
I'm on my laptop, so I'm
going to use the gloo backend.
OK, so now I'm here.
Pretend I have four of
these processes running.
So there's this barrier
function, which is useful as--
it's a synchronization barrier.
So basically, if I
see this, then it
waits for all the processes
to get to this point.
So basically, you can think
about all the processes
are running asynchronously.
So I don't really control.
One could completely
finish before the other.
They might finish
interleaved in any way.
So if I want to make
sure that there's
some code that is executed
before other code,
I put these synchronization
barriers in.
So now the downside of
putting more barriers in
is that, well, you end up
kind of waiting potentially
unnecessarily.
So let's try an all reduce.
So I'm going to create
this tensor, 0, 1, 2, 3.
And I have my rank.
Just to make it
more interesting,
each rank is going to
have a different tensor.
I'm going to print out what
I have before the all reduce.
So now I'm going to
skip over here and see
what gets printed out.
So rank 0 before all
reduce has 0, 1, 2, 3.
Rank 1 has 1, 2,
3, 4, and so on.
It's the same example
as I showed before.
Notice that the print statements
are coming in whatever order
the hardware feels like it,
because it's running async.
But all the data is there.
So now if I do all reduce,
and this you pass in--
this is a PyTorch function.
It passes in this tensor.
You pass in the reduction
operation, which is a sum.
And I'm going to
say don't do async.
And what this does is it calls,
in this case, it would be gloo,
but it could be NCCL,
in which case, it
would spin up the Cuda kernels.
It would do the communication.
It takes care of
everything for you.
And then it basically
writes in place to the data.
So after the all reduce, I
have the all reduce operation,
remember, which is the sum
of each of these columns
but replicated
across all the ranks.
So that's all reduce.
And if you wanted to be
fancier and do async,
then you could say
async equals true.
But then it would screw up
all these print statements.
So I'm trying to put more
barriers than I would normally
would.
Yeah, question?
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is
the rank the GPU.
For this class, the
rank is the GPU.
So let's try another
example here.
So I'm going to do
a reduce scatter.
So here, I'm going to
create an input, which
is 0 through the world size.
And I'm going to
have the output.
I'm going to
allocate the output.
And so what does this look like
before I do the reduce scatter?
It looks like, let's see,
this, where it's the same input
and the output
happens to be zeros,
but it could be just anything.
And then I do the
reduce scatter tensor.
Here instead of
writing in place,
I have an output tensor
and an input tensor.
I say I want to do
the sum and then
afterwards, I get basically
the input is not touched,
but the output I
get the reduction
of each component written
into the respective ranks.
So yeah, question?
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is,
how does it work
to do the all
reduces asynchronous?
So what this means is that this
is like a monolithic operation.
You say go do the all reduce.
And it's spinning
up Cuda kernels.
It's going to do
the communication.
And remember, Cuda is already
kind of async with respect
to the processes,
and now we have
all the processes being async.
And the point is that this
code just would return.
And then you could
do other things.
So a typical thing,
which I'm not
going to talk about this class,
is overlapping computation
and communication.
So for example, you
can do this operation,
and then you can go ahead
and load some other data
for the next step, which is
independent of this operation.
And then when you want to make
sure that you actually are done,
then you can call a
weight or a barrier.
So let's do the final
one, which is all gather.
So by now, I think
you get the idea.
Here I'm going to
set as the input
the output of the
reduce scatter.
I'm going to allocate an output.
So before the all gather,
it looks like this.
I have my results from
the reduce scatter here.
The output is just allocated.
It happens to have some values
in it, but don't worry about it.
And then after I do the
all gather into tensor,
and then I will have all the
different inputs gathered
onto all the different ranks.
And you can see
here that, indeed,
proof via example
that all reduce
is equal to reduce
scatter plus all gather.
And then just to wrap things up,
just as I started by setup, then
I clean up, which it's
good practice to clean up.
So that was your first example
of a Torch distributed program.
So let's do some benchmarking.
This will be quick, since I want
to actually move on to part two.
So how fast does
communication happen?
So let's do an all reduce.
So here, I'm going to all reduce
with 100 million elements.
Oops.
Sorry, I messed this up.
So all reduce.
So I'm going to
create this tensor
with this number of elements.
And remember, just like before
when we do benchmarking,
we warm up first.
And here, I'm going to call
the Cuda synchronize and also
the barrier, just to make
sure that because there's
two forms of asynchrony
here, the Cuda kernels
and the different processes.
And just want to
make sure everything
is kind of not running and is
done before I start the time.
And I'm going to
do the all reduce.
And then wait again with the
synchronize in the barrier
and stop the time.
So remember, this is running
for every single rank.
So if I look at the output,
here for rank 0, 2, 1, 3,
I have a different
time potentially,
because they're all
different processes.
Each of them is going to
report a certain measurement.
And if you want to
report one number,
you can take the
average, for example.
So now one thing
that is useful to do,
which is analogous to when
we were computing MFU,
is to measure the
effective bandwidth.
And the idea here is that, well,
this took 1.6 milliseconds.
How much-- is that good or bad?
So to compute the
effective bandwidth, what
we're going to do is
to compute essentially
how many bytes were
sent and should be
sent during this computation.
And then if you divide
by the total time,
then you get the
effective bandwidth.
So the size of what
I'm sending around
is the size of each element
times the number of elements.
So that's basically the number
of bytes of this data tensor.
How many bytes
get actually sent?
So this needs some unpacking.
So for all reduce,
if you think about,
let's just say for simplicity,
you do a rank 0 plus rank 1
plus rank 2 plus rank 3.
You need to iterate this
world size minus 1 steps,
because there's a world size
minus 1 addition operations.
So that's this factor.
There's a 2, because you
need to both send and reduce.
And then you multiply by
the size of the payload.
So that's the total
number of sent bytes.
And the total duration is the
wall clock time that it took.
And then you multiply
by the world size,
because it's the total amount
that all the ranks have waited.
And the bandwidth
is the bytes sent
divided by the total duration.
So in this case,
you get something
like about 400
gigabytes per second.
So a few notes here.
One is that the
effective bandwidth,
if you look at this
expression, size times 2 times
world size minus 1 divided
by world size times duration.
So as world size
increases, this world size
minus 1 divided by world size
essentially converges to 1.
So you're effectively
left with 2 times the size
bytes over the duration.
So this is essentially
the bandwidth.
Notice that this is
independent of the world size,
which is good.
So if you grow the
number of GPUs you have,
the bandwidth doesn't change.
It is also independent
of the topology, which
is something that kind of NCCL
figures out whether you're
going to pass the messages
in a kind of a ring or a tree
topology.
So yeah.
So that is all reduce.
And for reduce scatter,
this is very similar.
So I'm going to create the
inputs and the outputs,
warm up, perform the
operation, and time it.
So notice that the reduce
scatter has these timings.
And you can also measure the
effective bandwidth here,
the number of bytes
that were in the input.
You have the number of
bytes that were sent.
Here there is no 2x here.
And then the total duration,
you divide by that,
you get the bandwidth.
So here, the bandwidth is--
it should be very similar.
I guess sometimes there's
some stochasticity,
but it's in the kind of 400s.
So a few notes here.
All reduce is, remember,
as we stated, reduce
scatter plus an all gather.
And so all reduce, naturally, is
moving twice the amount of data,
because reduce scatter has some
cost, all gather has some cost,
and all reduce is doing
twice as much work.
And it takes twice
the amount of time.
But the two cancel out, so you
get the same kind of bandwidth.
So that is the end of part one.
Maybe any questions
before I move to part two?
Yeah.
Why did you do that
synchronized for [INAUDIBLE]?
So why do we have to do the
synchronized for the Cuda
kernel?
So at the end of the day, we
are still doing Cuda operations.
We have just multiple
processes, each with a GPU,
doing some Cuda operations.
So if you're doing a Cuda
operation, remember, by default,
it's async.
So when you reach the
next line in Python,
that Cuda operation
might not be done.
So we need to wait
always to make sure it's
done by synchronizing.
[INAUDIBLE]
So do you have to do barrier
first and then synchronize?
I'm not sure.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
I think one problem is
if you barrier first
and then the Cuda might
not be done running,
and you just immediately
go to the barrier.
And then you are still each
independently synchronizing
the different Cuda kernels,
which means that you're not
really synchronized.
If all those
operations just return,
the barrier doesn't
really do anything.
OK, let me move on.
So now let's actually
start thinking
about how you train models.
So we're just going to walk
through a very bare bones
implementation of training
MLPs, multilayer MLPs.
I guess that's redundant.
It's multilayer
perceptrons already.
And remember that
MLPs are the ones that
are the actual compute
bottleneck in the transformer.
So this is actually pretty
representative of what
you'll see.
So data parallelism,
tensor parallelism,
and pipeline parallelism.
And the picture I want
you to have in your head
is this picture.
So this is a little
bit of a schematic,
so don't think too
deeply about this,
but it's more of a way to
conceptualize how you're cutting
your data and parameters.
So data parallelism
says, I'm going
to split the data into pieces.
And then each of
the GPUs is going
to be responsible
for part of the data,
and I'm going to
just do normal--
I'm going to keep track
of all the parameters
and do normal model training.
And then I need to synchronize.
So let me explain
how this works.
So I'm going to generate
some sample data.
So there's a batch size of 128.
Number of dimensions, 1,024.
So this is a batch size by
num dim matrix, data matrix.
And let's jump into
this data parallelism.
So the way that
it's going to work
is that you have
this data matrix.
And I'm going to break up the
rows into world size pieces.
And in this case, four.
And each rank is
going to get a piece.
So the number of
dimensions, the batch size.
So I'm going to call the local
batch size, basically the batch
size divided by the
world size, which
is every row that GPU sees, it's
going to have 32 data points.
And this is just indexing.
Start index data start to end
gets you the slice of that data.
And I'm going to just
put it on that rank.
So at this point,
each GPU has now
a distinct data tensor,
which is the part
that they're responsible for.
Now, in practice, each
rank should probably
load its own data rather
than have this bottleneck,
but this is just for
illustrative purposes.
So let's instantiate the MLP.
So here, I assume
we have layers.
And num layers.
And for each of the layers,
I'm going to have just a num
dim by num dim matrix.
So I'm just going to initialize
a random set of parameters.
And then I'm going to
feed that into optimizer.
So here's the training loop.
So in the forward
pass, I take the data.
So remember, data
is not all the data.
It's just if I'm rank 2, then
I only get B2 part of the data.
I'm going to just go
through the number of layers
and do a forward pass.
And then I'm going to
do a backward pass.
And then normally,
this would be it.
But now, remember, every
rank has different data.
Therefore, the gradients are
going to be different as well.
So this is the key step that
makes data parallelism work.
We're going to
synchronize the gradients
across all the workers.
This is the only difference
between standard training
and DDP.
It's actually pretty
nice and elegant.
So basically, for
all the parameters,
I'm going to do an all
reduce of parem.grad.
And I'm going to average.
And then after this all reduce
is done, then now at this point,
each of the ranks has
the exact same gradients.
And then I'm just going
to update the parameters.
So it's kind of really
elegant, I find,
because it's basically standard
training where you apply it
to your local batch,
but you just insert this
after the backward pass.
Let's just average all the
gradients via this all reduce.
It's a one line code change, and
then the parameters get updated.
So as you're training,
each rank is basically
performing parameter updates as
if it had all the data on it,
but it's only actually
processing a part of the data.
So that's basically DDP or the
first type of data parallel.
Any questions about this?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is,
can you only do this
with batch size greater than 1?
Yes.
So your batch size has to be
at least world size for this
to really make sense.
And usually, it should
probably be quite a bit larger.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So the question is,
should the batch size
be a multiple of world size?
And that also would be nice.
Yes.
I mean, if it's not,
then you can pad it
with zeros or something.
So there's ways, but it's just
easier for everyone if it is.
[INAUDIBLE]?
What would it look like for a
transform-based [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, so the question
is, what would this look
like for a transformer?
It would actually be
basically the same.
The DDP has the nice thing
that is very modular.
You do the forward pass.
I mean, DDP just averages
the parameters here.
It doesn't care what your
forward pass looks like.
OK, let me move on.
So that's DDP.
So just to summarize, the losses
are different across the ranks.
The gradients are also
initially different.
But they are all reduced to
be the same across the ranks.
And therefore,
the parameters all
remain the same across ranks.
So next lecture,
[? Tatsu ?] is going
to talk about fancier data
parallelism, FSDP and 0.
And the idea there is,
as I've alluded to,
here we use all reduce.
It's a very simple
monolithic operation,
but it does require holding
all the models, parameters
in memory.
But what if the model
parameters don't fit in memory?
Then you're going to
have to be more clever,
and that's the topic
for the next class.
So let me talk about
tensor parallelism.
So here, the idea is we're
going to cut this way
and we're not going
to cut the data.
We're going to cut
essentially each layer.
And so each rank is going
to get part of each layer.
And generally, this
means that we're
going to have to
transfer a lot more data.
We'll discuss this a bit later.
So what does tensor
parallel look like?
So we're just going to
assume we have this data.
Every rank has all the
data just for simplicity.
And here, remember, the data
is batch size times num dim.
And I'm going to
define a local num dim
dim to be-- for
this rank, I only
am responsible for a
subset of the dimensions.
So the picture here is that each
model still has all the layers
here for all the layers,
but the parameters now
are num dim times local num dim.
So if this were one
of the parameter
matrices for one layer, I would
be splitting down the columns.
So this is also known as
column tensor parallel.
You can also do it by
rows, but we're not going
to talk about that right now.
So now what does the
forward pass look like?
So I'll go through
all the layers
and I'm going to
compute activations.
So I start with x the data.
And I'm going to access
the parameters at layer.
And notice that this is only
a slice of the parameters.
So if I'm on rank 1, I only
get this part of the matrix.
But I can still proceed.
I can apply this
non-linearity, because this
is element wise anyway.
But now what I'm going
to do is I'm going
to communicate activations.
So if I have a
data matrix, rank 1
has activations for
part of the activations
for this part of the matrix.
Rank 1 has part of the
activations for this matrix
and so on and so forth.
And I need to basically
put all the activations
on all the ranks.
But we know how to do that.
We introduced all gather
as a collective primitive.
So this is all the activations.
So this is the batch size
times local num dim, which is
the shape of the activations.
And then I'm doing
an all gather.
Sorry, so this is the allocating
memory for the activations.
So x is the actual
part of the activation.
So this is batch size
times local num dim.
And all gather says each
rank has x and each rank
is going to allocate
activations,
which is a list, one
for each world size.
And then after the
all gather, x is
going to be copied into each
of the respective location
activations.
So then once I gather
all the activations,
I concatenate them to form
the full dimensional x, which
is batch size times num dim.
Any questions about
column tensor parallel?
So this is done for every layer.
We now notice one difference
between data parallel
is now we have to muck
around with the model.
Data parallel is very elegant,
because it's splitting by data.
The model is
treated as a module.
But now we have to muck
around with the model.
And this is strongly
leveraging the fact
that if you want to do
a matrix multiplication,
you can split it up into
a set of smaller matrix
multiplications.
We can do those on
different ranks,
and then we can
gather the results.
When it comes to the
back propagation,
[INAUDIBLE] gradients
are still [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
So now the question is,
what happens in backprop?
Now, in the backprop,
you have your activations
and you have to reduce scatter
to all the different gradients.
So in some ways, all
gather and reduce scatter
have this kind of duality,
where in forward, you're
all gathering, in the backward,
you're reduce scattering.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, is that
done automatically by autograd?
So none of this--
well, OK.
So if you just call .backward,
it's not going to do it,
because there's no
parallelism in that.
But PyTorch has all
these things that
are done automatically for you.
[INAUDIBLE] To what
extent do I need to change
my code and [INAUDIBLE]?
So what is done for you
and versus automatically?
Here we're managing
things fairly explicitly,
which means I'm not
doing the backward pass,
but you would have to manage
and call the reduce scatter
yourself.
And that's by design,
because this is 336,
building language
models from scratch.
In practice, you probably
wouldn't have to do that.
OK, so let's do pipeline
parallelism quickly.
So the idea behind
pipeline parallelism
is we're going to split
the network this way.
So each rank is going to get
a subset of the layers now.
Within each layer, it's going
to get all the dimensions,
and it's also going
to get all the--
well, one of the ranks is
going to get all the data.
Every rank is going to see
all the data in some form.
So this is the way
it's going to work.
So we have all the
data, which is, again,
the batch size times num dim.
And I'm going to
split up the layers.
So local num layers is going
to be the number of layers
that a particular rank
is going to handle.
And so now I'm going to
have local params, which
is basically only-- there's
local number of layers
number of them.
But within each layer, I'm going
to do the num dim by num dim.
So one thing, maybe
[INAUDIBLE] will talk more
about this on Wednesday, is
this idea of micro-batches.
So maybe I'll just
present this and explain
why I'm doing things this way.
So in addition to
splitting up the layers,
I'm also going to
split up the batch
into a bunch of micro-batches.
So if I'm rank 0,
then I get the data,
and I'm going to chunk it up
into a number of micro-batches.
And for each micro-batch,
what I'm going to do
is receive it from
the previous rank,
and then do the feed forward
pass only on the layers that
are assigned to this rank.
And then I'm going to
send to the next rank.
So here I'm actually using
these receive and send,
which are pointwise operations.
So I didn't cover those before,
but they're fairly explanatory.
This basically says
I'm rank and I'm going
to send this tensor over to--
sorry, I'm going to receive
this tensor from rank minus 1.
And this says I'm going to
send tensor x to rank plus 1.
So basically, the reason why I'm
talking about micro-batches is--
and [? Tatsu ?] will talk
more about this on Wednesday--
is that in pipeline
parallelism, so you have
one rank that gets the data.
It processes some of
the layers, and then
it sends it to the next GPU, and
it process some of the layers.
And it then sends
it to the next GPU.
So this is a very natural way
of dividing a deep network.
But the problem is
that you get these
what are called pipeline
bubbles, where while you're not
processing, you're kind of
waiting around for other tensors
to process.
And this ends up being
quite inefficient.
So the idea behind micro-batches
is that you break it up
into smaller batches, so
you can process it quickly,
send it on to the next one.
So this can reduce the
number of pipeline bubbles.
So the other thing
I will mention
that is not handled in this
very kind of naive version
is the idea of overlapping
communication and computation,
which is actually very important
to pipeline parallelism.
This basically gives
you the right structure.
If you put an I before these,
then it becomes kind of async.
You have to add more
things to manage the code.
And the idea here is
that you want to be--
while you're computing
here, you can be
receiving data or sending data.
So computation and
communication should overlap.
So that reduces the amount of
time you actually spend waiting.
So a few things that are kind
of missing here, which we'll
hopefully fill in next time.
So the communication
versus computation overlap,
which is especially crucial
in pipeline parallelism.
I didn't mention in
data parallelism,
this also happens, because
I just did a forward pass
and then at the end, I'm just
doing all these all reduces.
But if you're clever,
then on the backward pass,
as soon as the
gradients are done,
you can start sending that.
And that's something
that will be
explored in the assignment two.
And this, again, allows you
to just overlap communication
and computation more.
We had some questions about
what about general models.
Again, I think
this MLP gives you
essentially most
of what you need
for understanding the basics.
Some of the larger models just
require a lot more bookkeeping,
so it's harder to see
the core algorithms.
There are other
types of parallelism
that we haven't covered.
So sequence parallelism
takes a whole sequence
and chops it up into pieces.
And that allows you to
parallelize the attention
computation, expert parallelism,
which allows you to parallelize
the experts for MOEs.
And this is where the all to
all that I mentioned comes in.
And then also
different combinations
of different parallelization
techniques, which also
will show up in the assignment.
So one thing to
note is that which
parallelism technique
you choose is
going to be strongly
dependent on the hardware.
For example, tensor parallelism.
There's a lot of communication,
because for every layer,
you need to send all
these activations, which
are fairly big.
So generally, tensor parallelism
happens within a node on NVLink
or where you have
high bandwidth.
Whereas you wouldn't
do tensor parallelism
past an NVLink domain.
Whereas a pipeline parallelism,
you'll see people using it.
And generally, this can tolerate
much slower interconnects.
So some of the
decentralized training work
uses pipeline parallel,
because your nodes are--
GPUs are halfway
across the world.
But you wouldn't want to do
tensor parallel in that setting.
So sometimes when you look
at these combinations,
it will be tensor
parallel within a node
and then pipe data
parallel or FSDP
and then pipeline
parallelism if you need it.
There's other effects, such
as if you do data parallel,
you might be able to do
data parallel quite a bit.
But then you start
hitting to something
called the critical
batch size, where
if you start increasing
the batch size too much,
it doesn't actually
help you, in which case
you're kind of
wasting your compute
and then you're better
off using tensor parallel.
So there's a bunch of
these considerations,
which we'll talk more about
as we go through the class.
So final note.
So TPUs came up a little bit.
One thing to note is that on
purpose, we are using PyTorch
and not just using
PyTorch, but really using
the collective operations
in a very primitive way,
so you can see mechanically
what's happening.
Another approach, especially if
you're in [INAUDIBLE] TPU land,
is that you can simply define
the model and the starting
strategy.
And the compiler
actually handles a lot
of the decision of how to--
basically, what kind of
communication operations
you need.
You basically say,
well, this piece of data
needs to be here
and here and here.
And then the compiler does
some magic to figure out what.
So that's appealing.
But obviously, it would
take a lot of the joy
out of actually building
things from scratch.
Just to summarize, so there's
many ways to parallelize.
You can cut by data,
cut by tensor or expert,
cut by pipeline or sequence.
We looked at data parallelism.
We only did DDP.
Next time we'll do FSDP and 0.
Tensor parallelism,
as I mentioned,
requires very fast
interconnects.
Pipeline less so.
But you need to really work
hard to reduce these pipeline
bubbles.
And then maybe at
a high level, we
see this pattern come up a lot.
So you can either recompute
or store in memory
when we were
talking about things
like activation checkpointing
or when we're working with GPUs.
Or in this case, you can think
about an extension of this
as that you can store
on a different GPU.
From that perspective, you
look at the data parallel.
You're doing redundant
work in some sense,
because every rank is actually
updating its parameters
and keeping track of
all the parameters.
But the reason
you're doing that is
that you don't have to move
the optimizer state across.
So one thing is that
hardware is getting faster.
But in some sense, we'll
always want bigger models.
So this idea of having
a hierarchical structure
will always be there.
So that's it for today.
So next Wednesday, [? Tatsu ?]
will do more of a deep dive
on more parallelism techniques.